Finding Aid for William G. Milliken papers 1961-1982
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
William G. Milliken papers 1961-1982
Milliken, William G., 1922-
Republican governor of Michigan, 1969-1982. Papers include governor's office correspondence, administrative and subject files, staff files, materials relating to his campaigns for governor and Republican Party affairs, and a limited amount of photographs and sound recordings.
8924 Aa 2
1000 linear feet at Bentley Historical Library approximate
700 linear feet at Michigan State Archives approximate
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
December 1982: Received 850 feet from State Record Center Storage and 850 feet from Capitol; November 1983: Received 150 feet from Milliken's Traverse City Office. Donor No. 7522.
The collection is open for research.
William Grawn Milliken was governor of Michigan from 1969-1982, the longest term in state history. A Yale-educated businessman and politician, he was elected Lieutenant Governor in 1964 and 1966, after serving four years in the State Senate, the last two as majority floor leader. He assumed the governorship on January 22, 1969, when George Romney resigned to become secretary of the United States Department of Housing and Urban Development in Richard Nixon's cabinet. Michigan voters returned Milliken to office in the 1970, 1974, and 1978 elections. His first gubernatorial victory was narrow, with just a 44,000 vote margin. But citizen favor for him grew, and by 1978, his last test at the polls, Milliken won by nearly 400,000 votes. Many of his supporters were ticket-splitters or former Democrats.
Although chief executive during the deepest economic crisis experienced in Michigan since the Depression, Governor Milliken was generally popular among both the people of the state and his political peers. A well-regarded politician, he chaired the National Governor's Association during 1977-1978 and the Midwest Governor's Association in 1974. He was the principal leader of the state GOP and a national force in the moderate wing of the Republican Party. Conservative elements within the party were often critical of the bipartisan, alliance-building style that led him to court labor, occasionally appoint Democrats to state jobs, and supported pro-choice legislation on abortion.
Milliken led the state during a conflict-ridden era that frequently tested his ability as a crisis manager--for example, the General Motors strike of 1970, two Arab oil embargoes, contamination of the food chain with the toxic chemical PBB, and a controversy surrounding the state mental health system. He was admired for a firmness of conviction on issues that mattered greatly to him, such as the responsibility of government to cities, the arts, the environment, and the poor. The state revenue sharing program that helped Detroit during troubled economic times was adopted largely through Milliken's efforts. His administration was noted for its commitment to conservation and the passage of the Environmental Protection Act of 1970, which serve a model legislation throughout the nation; the budget stabilization fund and efforts at economic development; and, in the last days of his term, worker and unemployment compensation reforms and enactment of a transportation package. Milliken announced his decision not to seek reelection on December 22, 1981. After retiring from public office, he joined Chrysler Corporation's board of directors and chaired the Center for the Great Lakes, a private economic and environmental research center devoted to protecting regional lake resources.
William Milliken was born in Traverse City on March 26, 1922, to James Thacker Milliken and Hildegarde Grawn. A waist-gunner on a World War II B-24 bomber, he received military honors, including the Purple Heart, for participation in 50 combat missions. From 1947-1955, he served on the Michigan Waterways Commission. The U.S. State Department selected him in 1953 to spend 75 days in West Germany in an intercultural exchange program and in 1971 to tour the Soviet Union and Romania. Governor Milliken is a past president of J.W. Milliken, Inc., a Michigan department store chain headquartered in Traverse City, with outlets in Manistee and Cadillac. His wife is the former Helen Wallbank of Denver, Colorado; they have two children, William, Jr. and Elaine.
The Milliken papers are organized in six subgroups: Correspondence, Administrative/Executive, Regional Offices, Political, Miscellaneous, and Audio-Visual Material. The Correspondence subgroup contains routine constituent incoming and outgoing mail and scattered policy-related materials. Items are indexed by correspondent in the master suspense card file. The Administrative/Executive subgroup includes the collection's core policy documents. Regional Offices consists of policy and operational materials on the governors official outposts. The Political subgroup contains sequences on the governor's appointments to office, fundraising and campaigns for the governorship, participation in presidential elections, and participation in the state and national Republican party. Miscellaneous subgroup contains papers created while Milliken served as Lieutenant Governor; audits, conference proceedings, task force recommendations, and general reports. Audio-Visual Materials includes the collection’s scant holdings of artifacts, photographs, scrapbooks, and sound recordings.
Some peculiarities characterize the files. Users should note that correspondence appears as both a subgroup and type of document found in all principal series. Folder headings are titled inconsistently throughout the inventory. Files on the same topic may appear in one series under a subject title, in another by geographic location, and in a third by the name of participant. To insure a thorough search, scan the contents list for all conceivable headings.
Summary Contents List
Correspondence
Chronological (Boxes 1-554; 1538) (Transferred to the Michigan State Archives)
1969
General Subjects (Boxes 1-8)
Departments and Commissions (Boxes 8-27)
Federal (Boxes 27-30)
Legislative (Boxes 30-32)
1970
General Subjects (Boxes 32-39)
Departments and Commissions (Boxes 39-66)
Federal (Boxes 66-70)
Legislative (Boxes 70-72)
1971
General Subjects (Boxes 72-80)
Departments and Commissions (Boxes 80-103)
Federal (Boxes 104-105)
Legislative (Boxes 105-106)
1972
General Subjects (Boxes 106-114)
Departments and Commissions (Boxes 114-137)
Federal (Boxes 137-138)
Legislative (Boxes 138-139)
1973
General Subjects (Boxes 140-148)
Departments and Commissions (Boxes 148-172)
Federal (Boxes 172-174)
Legislative (Boxes 174-178)
1974
General Subjects (Boxes 179-191)
Departments and Commissions (Boxes 191-222)
Federal (Boxes 222-223)
Legislative (Boxes 223-225)
1975
General Subjects (Boxes 226-237)
Departments and Commissions (Boxes 237-270)
Federal (Boxes 270-272)
Legislative (Boxes 272-274)
1976
General Subjects (Boxes 274-285)
Departments and Commissions (Boxes 286-311)
Federal (Boxes 311-313)
Legislative (Boxes 313-314)
1977
General Subjects (Boxes 315-325)
Departments and Commissions (Boxes 326-354)
Federal (Boxes 355-356; 1538)
Legislative (Boxes 356-357)
1978
General Subjects (Boxes 357-367)
Departments and Commissions (Boxes 368-395)
Federal (Boxes 396-397)
Legislative (Boxes 397-398)
1979
General Subjects (Boxes 399-406)
Departments and Commissions (Boxes 407-433)
Federal (Boxes 433-434)
Legislative (Boxes 434-435)
1980
General Subjects (Boxes 436-447)
Departments and Commissions (Boxes 447-475)
Federal (Boxes 475-477)
Legislative (Boxes 477)
1981
General Subjects (Boxes 478-490)
Departments and Commissions (Boxes 490-518)
Federal (Boxes 518-520)
Legislative (Boxes 520-521)
1982
General Subjects (Boxes 521-530)
Departments and Commissions (Boxes 530-552)
Federal (Boxes 552-554)
Legislative (Boxes 554)
Study Commissions, 1969-1982 (Boxes 558-572)
Additional Correspondence (Boxes 1474-1493; 1541-1595)
Special Letters (Boxes 1474-1477)
Petitions and Citizen Mail (Boxes 1477-1486)
TWX Messages (Boxes 1487-1489)
Unfiled Correspondence (Boxes 1490-1493)
Governor Personal, 1969-1982 (Boxes 1541-1595)
Multiple (Robo) Responses (Boxes 1619-1771) Transferred to State Archives
Administrative /Executive
State Administrative Board, 1968-1982 (Boxes 573-587)
Internal Memoranda and Correspondence (Boxes 595-626)
Governor's (Boxes 595-596)
Staff
1969-1973 (Boxes 596-599)
1974 (Boxes 599-600)
1975 (Boxes 600-601)
1976 (Boxes 602-604)
1977 (Boxes 604-606)
1978 (Boxes 606-608)
1979 (Boxes 608-611)
1980 (Boxes 611-614)
1981 (Boxes 614-618)
1982 (Boxes 618-622)
Subject Files (Boxes 623-626)
Office of Lt. Governor (Boxes 627-628)
Gordon Alexander (Boxes 629-632)
Glenn Allen (Boxes 632-635)
Holly Angell (Boxes 636-639)
Patrick Babcock (Boxes 640-649)
Janis Bocskay (Boxes 650-652)
Barbara Debrodt (Boxes 653-655)
Tom DeCair (Boxes 656-658)
Dave Duncan (Boxes 659-661)
Peter Ellsworth/Ken Frankland (Boxes 662-705)
Christine Fedewa (Boxes 706-708)
Steven M. Fetter (Boxes 709-710)
Glenn Friedly (Boxes 710-715)
Don Gordon (Boxes 716-718)
Jeff Graham (Boxes 719-724)
Billie Harrison (Boxes 724-728)
Richard Helmbrecht (Box 729)
William Hettiger (Boxes 730-738)
Phil Kazmierski/Tom Drake (Boxes 739-753)
James Kellogg/Mark Mason (Boxes 754-763)
Bob Law (Boxes 763-774)
William Long (Boxes 775-779)
William Lukens (Boxes 780-781)
Richard McLellan (Boxes 782-783)
Marc Obershulte (Box 783)
Dennis M. Payne (Boxes 784-786)
Stanley C. Pratt (Boxes 787-789)
Craig Ruff (Boxes 789-790)
Bill Rustem (Boxes 790-794)
Isabella Saxton (Boxes 795-804)
Libby Schleiffarth (Box 805)
Linda Slotsema (Boxes 806-814)
Kathy Stariha (Boxes 815-822)
Manfred Tatzmann (Boxes 822-823)
George Weeks (Boxes 824-845)
Miscellaneous Early Program (Boxes 846-850)
Briefings (Boxes 972-1028)
Daily Commitments (Boxes 972-1022)
Appointments/Scheduling (Boxes 972-974)
Memoranda (Boxes 974-976)
Speaking Commitments (Boxes 977-1022)
Topical Files (Boxes 1023-1028)
Michigan House Bills and Senate Bills (Boxes 1053-1169)
Unofficial Amended Resolutions, Bills, and Bill Analyses (Boxes 1053-1163)
Topical Files (Boxes 1163-1169)
Press Office (Boxes 1206-1228)
Master Press Releases (Boxes 1206-1214)
Newspaper Column "Ask the Governor" (Box 1214)
Press Conference Transcripts (Boxes 1215-1216)
Special Messages (Box 1217)
Speeches (Boxes 1217-1218)
Topical Files (Boxes 1219-1228)
Regional Offices
Detroit/Urban Affairs (Boxes 901-935)
Upper Peninsula (Boxes 936-944)
Washington, D.C. (Boxes 945-948)
Political
Appointments (Boxes 1283-1407)
Boards, Commissions, Task Forces (Boxes 1283-1354)
Master Index (Fragmentary) (Box 1283)
Summary Information and Lists (Box 1283)
Topical (Boxes 1284-1347)
Colleges/Universities (Boxes 1348-1351)
County Jury Boards (Boxes 1352-1353)
Social Services Board (Box 1353)
Study Commissions (Box 1354)
Judicial (Boxes 1355-1379)
Circuit Court (Boxes 1355-1361)
Common Pleas (Box 1362)
Court of Appeals (Box 1363)
District Court (Boxes 1364-1371)
Probate Court (Boxes 1372-1376)
Recorders Court (Boxes 1377-1378)
Supreme Court (Box 1379)
Miscellaneous (Box 1379)
Persons Appointed (Boxes 1380-1403)
Public Administrators (Box 1404)
Recall Positions (Box 1404)
Special Assistant Attorney General (Box 1404)
Office Files/Joce Braithwaite (Boxes 1405-1408)
Campaigns (Boxes 1408-1426)
1970 (Boxes 1408-1410)
1974 (Boxes 1410-1414)
1978 (Boxes 1414-1424)
1982 (Boxes 1425-1426)
Republican Party (Boxes 1426-1438)
Fundraising (Boxes 1426-1429)
Michigan (Boxes 1430-1437)
National (Boxes 1437-1438)
Miscellaneous
Lieutenant Governor, 1961-1972 (Boxes 1439-1442)
Reports (Boxes 1443-1449)
Topical (Boxes 1443-1449)
Special Reports of the Governor (Box 1449)
Departments and Commissions (Box 1449)
Audio-Visual Material
Artifacts (Box 1450)
Photographs (Box 1451)
Scrapbooks (Box 1452)
Sound Recordings (Boxes 1772-1773)
The William G. Milliken Papers is the most important source available for the study of Michigan's state government from 1969-1982. The collection currently measures 1478 linear feet and includes correspondence, memoranda, reports, agenda and minutes, briefing books, press releases and public statements, legal briefs and decisions, legislative bills and bill analyses, clippings, and printed works that pertain to Milliken's years as governor. Half of the papers arrived at the Bentley Historical Library in December 1982, from State Record Center retirement. Another portion came directly from the Capitol Complex at the end of Milliken's term. Several hundred feet arrived in 1983 from the governor's Traverse City office. Smaller accessions related to politics and political appointments were received in the late 1980s.
Materials in the collection concern the official conduct of state government including the governor's role in legislative activity; the interface of state-federal jurisdictions; and the administration of the executive office, departments, commissions, and regional offices. The papers provide a rich resource for the study of executive response to concerns such as economic development, hazardous wastes, civil rights and affirmative action, labor, energy, minority populations, education, urban development, sex discrimination, and regional issues. As the governor remained active in the Republican party and sought election three times, the collection also includes materials on political matters. Files created by Milliken while Lieutenant Governor appear as well.
Subjects:
Michigan--Politics and government--1961-1970.; Michigan--Politics and government--1971-1980.; Michigan--Politics and government--1981-1990.; Milliken, William G., 1922-; Governors--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Apartment houses--Michigan--East Lansing.; Copper mining--Michigan.; East Lansing (Mich.)--Apartment houses.; Jackson (Mich.)--Prison facilities.; Milliken, William G., 1922-; Prison facilities--Michigan--Jackson.; State Prison of Southern Michigan.; White Pine Copper Company.; White Pine (Mich.); Governors--Michigan.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Correspondence
  The Milliken Correspondence is organized into several series and subseries. The largest is a Chronological file with subdivisions in each year for General Subjects, Departments and Commissions, Federal and Legislative Smaller series include Study Commissions, Special Letters, Petitions/Citizen's Mail, Governor's Personal Correspondence and mechanically generated Robo Mail. All of the Chronological Correspondence Files (1969-1982, Boxes 1-554, 558-572, 1538), the Study Commissions Correspondence (Boxes 558-572) and the ROBO letters (Boxes 1619-1771) have been transferred to the State of Michigan Archives.
  - Chronological 1969-1982, 554 linear feet
    General Subjects is a chronological subject file arranged alphabetically by correspondent's last name that consists entirely of topical incoming citizen letters and petitions. Attached to each inquiry is the governor's or staff member's response. Access material by name (see card index system) or subject (refer to master list of headings).
    The Departments and Commissions correspondence is a chronological run of records arranged by year and thereunder alphabetically by department or commission. Some headings are directly followed by files titled Director or Material. These folders contain resource material that may include correspondence, memos, budgets, annual reports, audits, minutes, press releases, reports, and printed matter. Items of this type appear most often for the earlier years and are only a fraction of the files. The bulk of the files consists of citizen complaints relevant to particular government offices.
    Filing idiosyncrasies exist. In 1973 the Department of Administration became the Department of Management and Budget. It assumed responsibility for the Bureau of programs and Budget (detailed in Michigan Manual, 1973-1974, pp. 281-286). Beginning in 1976, a new folder title, Volunteers in Michigan, appears. The physical placement of this file suggests independent commission status, but it is actually a subdepartment of the Department of Management and Budget. Beginning in 1980 the Department of Highways appears as Transportation and Police as State Police.
    Correspondence can be accessed by name (see card index system) or department (see master list below). Policy materials related to this sequence may be found in the Staff Files and Internal Memoranda and Correspondence series.
    Federal Correspondence is comprised principally of constituent correspondence related to federal legislation or regulations. Material is arranged by subject until 1978; beginning in 1979, items are filed alphabetically by the correspondent's name. Policy materials related to this sequence may be found in the Staff Files, Internal Memoranda and Correspondence, Washington Office, and Political series. Correspondence can be accessed by name (see the card index system) or by subject for the years 1969-1978 (see master list below).
    The Legislative correspondence contains constituent mail regarding pending legislation. Material is arranged alphabetically by correspondent's name, with some topical headings for earlier years. Policy materials related to this sequence may be found in most other series. Access by name (see card index system) or subject (see master list below).
    - 1969
      - General Subjects
        - A-E (Box 1)
        - E (Box 2)
        - E-L (Box 3)
        - L (Box 4)
        - L-R (Box 5)
        - R-Z (Box 6)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
        - A-Mc (Box 7)
        - M-Z (Box 8)
      - Departments and Commissions
        - Administration
          - Director's File (Glenn S. Allen) (Box 8)
          - General, A-Z, 5 folders (Box 8)
          - Budget Division
            - General (Box 8)
            - Building (Box 8)
            - Capitol Complex (Box 8)
          - Council for the Arts (Box 8)
          - Meetings (Box 8)
          - Retirement Boards (Box 9)
          - Retirement, Judges (Box 9)
          - Retirement System, Employees (Box 9)
          - Retirement System, School Employees (Box 9)
          - Senior Citizens' Homestead (Tax Exemption) (Box 9)
          - Veteran's Trust Fund, A-Z, 4 folders (Box 9)
          - Washington, George (former Director) (Box 9)
        - Agriculture
          - Director's File (B. Dale Ball) (Box 9)
          - General
            - A-R (Box 9)
            - S-Z (Box 10)
          - Cherry Commission Fair Authority (Box 10)
          - Gorcers Baking Company (Diet Rite Bread) (Box 10)
          - Insecticides and Pesticides (Box 10)
          - Michigan State Fair Authority (Box 10)
          - Racing Commission (Box 10)
          - Upper Peninsula Fair Authority (Box 10)
        - Attorney General
          - Frank J. Kelley (Box 10)
          - General, A-Z, 4 folders (Box 10)
          - Opinions (Box 10)
        - Auditor General (Report) (Box 10)
        - Civil Rights
          - Director's File (Burton I. Gordin) (Box 10)
          - General, A-Z, 4 folders (Box 10)
        - Civil Service
          - Director's File (Franklin K. DeWald) (Box 10)
          - General
            - A-F (Box 10)
            - General G-Z (Box 11)
          - Compensation Manual (Box 11)
        - Commerce
          - Director's File (Richard E. Whitmer) (Box 11)
          - General, A-Z, 4 folders (Box 11)
          - Aeronautics Board (Box 11)
          - Banking Commission (Box 11)
          - Cemetery Commission (Box 11)
          - Economic Expansion (Box 11)
          - Great Markwestern Slaughterhouse Company (Albion) (Box 11)
          - Insurance Commission, A-Z, 4 folders (Box 12)
          - Liquor Control Commission, A-Z, 4 folders (Box 12)
          - Public Service Commission, A-Z, 5 folders (Box 12)
          - St. Lawrence Seaway (10th Anniversary), 3 folders (Box 12)
          - Upper Great Lakes Regional Economic Development Commission (Box 12)
          - Upper Peninsula Committee for Area Progress (Box 12)
        - Corrections
          - Director's File (Gus Harrison) (Box 12)
          - Inmates
            - A-L (Box 12)
            - M-Z (Box 13)
          - Pardons and Paroles (Box 13)
        - Education: General
          - Director's File (Ira Polley) (Box 13)
          - General, A-Z (Box 13)
          - Deaf, School for the (Box 14)
          - Deaf-Mute Letters (Box 14)
          - Family Helper Program (Box 14)
          - State Library, Closing of (Box 14)
          - Vocational Rehabilitation (Box 14)
          - West Bloomfield School District (Annual Report) 1968-1969 (Box 14)
        - Education: Colleges and Universities
          - General, A-Z (Box 14)
          - Central Michigan University (Box 14)
          - Community College District (Box 14)
          - Eastern Michigan University (Box 14)
          - Ferris State College (Box 14)
          - Grand Valley State College (Box 14)
          - Michigan State University (Box 14)
          - Northern Michigan University (Box 14)
          - Osteopathic Colleges (Box 14)
          - University of Michigan (Box 14)
          - Wayne State University (Box 14)
          - Western Michigan University (Box 14)
        - Highways
          - Director's File (Howard E. Hill -- contains Henrik Stafseth material) (Box 14)
          - General
            - A-Z, 4 folders (Box 15)
            - I-696, A-Z (Box 15)
            - U.S. 24 (Telegraph Road) (Box 15)
            - Eighteenth Annual Progress Report (Box 15)
            - Great Lakes Commission (Box 15)
            - Inter-Agency Transportation Council (Box 15)
            - International Bridge Authority (Box 15)
            - Mackinac Bridge Authority (Box 15)
            - Trees (Box 15)
        - Labor
          - Director's File (Thomas Roumell) (Box 15)
          - General
            - A-L (Box 15)
            - M-Z (Box 16)
          - Labor Mediation Board, 2 folders (Box 16)
          - Manpower Training (Box 16)
          - Michigan Employment Security Commission
            - Director's File (Malcolm Lovell) (Box 16)
            - General, A-Z (Box 16)
          - Workmen's Compensation
            - General, A-Z, 4 folders (Box 16)
            - Appeal Board (Box 16)
        - Licensing and Regulation
          - Director's File (Lenton A. Sculthorpe) (Box 16)
          - General, A-Z (Box 16)
          - Accountancy Board (Box 16)
          - Architects Board (Box 16)
          - Athletic Board of Control (Box 16)
          - Barber Board (Box 16)
          - Chiropractic Board (Box 17)
          - Cosmetology Board (Box 17)
          - Dentistry Board (Box 17)
          - Electrical Board (re: Hearing Aid) (Box 17)
          - Medicine Board (Box 17)
          - Mortuary Board (Box 17)
          - Nursing Board (Box 17)
          - Optometry Board (Box 17)
          - Physical Therapy Division (Box 17)
          - Plumbing Board (Box 17)
          - Podiatry Board (Box 17)
          - Private Employment Bureaus (Box 17)
          - Psychologists, Certification of (Box 17)
          - Real Estate Board (Box 17)
        - Mental Health
          - Director's File (William H. Anderson) (Box 17)
          - General
            - A-R (Box 17)
            - S-Z (Box 18)
          - Budget (Box 18)
          - Caro State Hospital (Box 18)
          - Petition for State Aid for Mental Hospitals (Box 18)
        - Military Affairs
          - G.R. Edwards File (Box 18)
          - Clarence E. Schnipke File (Box 18)
          - Adjutant General (Box 18)
          - Homestead Tax, A-Z (Box 18)
          - Military Affairs Naval Board (Box 18)
          - National Guard, A-Z, 4 folders (Box 18)
          - Selective Service (Box 18)
          - Veterans, A-Z, 4 folders (Box 18)
          - Veterans Bonus (Box 18)
        - Natural Resources
          - Director's File (Ralph A. MacMullen) (Box 19)
          - General
            - A-M (Box 19)
            - N-Z (Box 20)